Guide to William Kruskal Papers 1964-1973
University of Chicago Library
Kruskal, William. Papers
1964-1973
1 linear ft. (2 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
William Kruskal, professor of statistics. The William Kruskal Papers consist of materials relating to student protests at the University of Chicago and elsewhere in 1969. Although this represents the bulk of the papers in the collection, there are also materials on the Harris Committee materials concerning an Afro-American Cultural Center, the Wegener Report, the Spartacus Report, the Gray Report on the status of women faculty, Edward H. Levi's correspondence, and materials from Kruskal's tenure as a member of the Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants (1964-1973). The papers in the collection include correspondence, memoranda, newspaper clipping, articles, and other materials.
Information on Use
Access
Access to Box 15, Folder 2 is restricted until 2019.
Biographical Note
William Henry Kruskal was born on October 10, 1919 in New York City to Joseph Bernard and Lillian Rose (Vorhaus) Kruskal. He received an S.B. (1940) and an M.S. (1941) from Harvard University and a Ph.D from Columbia University (1955).
From 1941 to 1944 Kruskal served as a mathematician for the U.S. Naval Proving Ground. This was followed by a term as vice president of Kruskal and Kruskal, Incorporated in New York from 1946 to 1948. In 1950 Kruskal joined the faculty of the University of Chicago. He became a professor of statistics there in 1962, and was honored as the Ernest DeWitt Burton Distinguished Service Professor in 1973. In addition to these duties, Kruskal was the chair of the department of statistics from 1966 to 1973 as well as the Dean of the Division of Social Sciences for a total of nine years. Kruskal also spent some time teaching at other universities including the University of California, Berkeley (1955-1956) and Harvard University (summer 1959).
Active in public and professional associations, Kruskal was president of both the American Statistical Association and the Institute of Mathematical Statistics, and was editor of the Annals of Mathematical Statistics and the International encyclopedia of Statistics. He was a National Science Foundation Senior Postdoctoral Fellow (1970-1971), a John Simon Guggenheim Fellow, and founding chairman of the Committee on National Statistics.
In 1988-1989, Kruskal was dean pro tempore of the Harris School of Public Policy at the University of Chicago. His research interests within statistics include graphical methods, history of statistics, linear hypothesis theory, measures of association, representative sampling, and the relative importance of independent variables. His research interests related to public policy include census errors, evaluation of research, measurement, and statistics in public controversy.
Kruskal married Norma Jane Evans on August 23, 1942. The couple had three children—Vincent Joseph, Thomas Evan, and Jonas David.
Scope Note
The William Kruskal Papers consist of materials relating to student protests at the University of Chicago and elsewhere in 1969. Although this represents the bulk of the papers in the collection, there are also materials on the Harris Committee materials concerning an Afro-American Cultural Center, the Wegener Report, the Spartacus Report, the Gray Report on the status of women faculty, Edward H. Levi's correspondence, and materials from Kruskal's tenure as a member of the Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants (1964-1973). The materials in the collection include correspondence, memoranda, newspaper clipping, articles, and other materials.
Folder 10 of Box 1 contains materials related to the 1969 "Spartacus" study. In "Spartacus: Discipline and Political Suppression: An Empirical Study," a group of social sciences graduate students criticized the University of Chicago's disciplinary committee, chaired by Dallin Oaks. This paper was presented as one of the occasional papers from the Committee of 500 Against Disciplinary Procedures. Kruskal collected materials related to the Spartacus statement, as well as Miron L. Straf's (a graduate student in the department of Statistics) rebuttal, "A Closer Look at Spartacus.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Levi, Edward H., Papers
Tax, Sol, Papers
Subject Headings
Hildebrand, Roger H.; Kruskal, William, 1919-; Levi, Edward Hirsch, 1911-; O'Connell, Charles D.; Tax, Sol; University of Chicago -- Committee of the Council; University of Chicago -Discipline; University of Chicago -- History; University of Chicago -- Riots; College students -- Political activity -- History -- 20th century; Student movements -- Illinois -- Chicago -- History; Student movements -- United States -- History
INVENTORY
- Articles on Student Protests, 1969, "16 Ousted From Harvard For Seizure of Building," New York Times, June 10, 1969 "Harvard Faculty Organizes in Response to Crisis," Science, July 4, 1969 "Activism and the Rejection of history," Science, July 11, 1969 "'Join the Conspiracy': A Summary of the Latest SDS Blueprint for Revolt," Barron's, July 21, 1969 "The University as a Five-Legged Animal," Science, August 15, 1969 "Revolution and Related Matters," The New Yorker, August 16, 1969 "On Keeping Our Cool in the Halls of Ivy," Thomas Ford Hoult et al., AAUP Bulletin, Summer 1969 "Challenge and Change Forum," AAUP Bulletin, Summer 1969 "Student Demands and Academic Freedom," The New Republic, September 20, 1969 "Yale Head Urges 7-Year Reappraisal of His Term, " New York Times, September 25, 1969 "15 War Foes Raid Harvard Center," September 26, 1969 "The University Responds to Protest," The Chicago Maroon, September 26, 1969 "Students May Cut Classes-Faculty Action Could Compromise Our Integrity," Faculty/Staff Currents, University of Rochester, October 7, 1969 (2 copies) "Harvard Faculty Urges a Pullout," New York Times, October 8, 1969 "Harvard Radicals Erode Authority," Chicago Sun-Times, October 29, 1969 "The Involuntary Campus and the Manipulated Society" Chicago Sun-Times, December 14, 1969 "The Record Thus Far: A Compilation of University Statements and Reports," 1969 The AAUP (American Association of University Professors) and Campus Disruption," pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Articles on Student Protests, 1969, Harvard Alumni Bulletin, April 28, 1969 "Going Over to the Enemy," dialogue with Robert Brustein, The New Republic, May 17, 1969 "Campus Reform: The Faculty Vote," Life Magazine, May 23, 1969 "Campus Riots: Punitive and Proper Laws," May 30, 1969 "Campus Reform: Numbers and Quality," Life Magazine, May 30, 1969 Harvard Today, Spring 1969 "Text of Statement on Campus Disorders by the National Violence Commission," New York Times, June 10, 1969 "ACE Study on Campus Unrest: Questions for Behavioral Scientists," Science, July 11, 1969 "The Siege of the House of Reason, " Science, October 10, 1969 "Men and Ideas: Columbia's New Senate," Fall 1969 "Faculty Interests in Value Change and Power Conflicts," T.R. McConnell, AAUP Bulletin, Autumn 1969 "Congress Looks at the Campus: The Brock Report on Student Unrest," AAUP Bulletin, Autumn 1969 "Student Protests," Jerome Skolnick, AAUP Bulletin, Autumn 1969 "Campus Unrest: Confrontation Increasingly Means Litigation," Science, Volume 166 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles on Student Protests, 1969, "New University Conference: The Student Rebellion," February 1969 "Harvard Report Urges 20% Cut in Graduate School Students," March 7, 1969 "Campus Disorders," The New Republic, March 29, 1969 College and University Reports, Number 198, March 31, 1969 The Chicago Maroon, Volume 77, Number 51, Friday, April 4, 1969 "Harvard: Now It's Like Any Other Paradise Lost," D.J.Bruckner, April 13, 1969 "Campus Activism," April 18, 1969 "End of Liberal Universities Foreseen," April 20, 1969 The Chicago Maroon, Volume 77, Number 55, Tuesday, April 22, 1969 "It's Time To Clamp Down on Campus Disruption," Max Lerner, April 24, 1969 "The Case for Professionalism," Robert Brustein, The New Republic, April 26, 1969 "One Man's View of the Unquiet Campus," William V. Shannon, April 28, 1969 "Crisis and Responsibility: A Letter to Alumni," Edward Rosenheim, Jr., University of Chicago Magazine, March/April 1969 "When, If Ever, Do You Call In the Cops?," New York Times Magazine, May 4, 1969 The Chicago Maroon, Volume 77, Number 61, Friday, May 9, 1969 "Oxford Committee Urges Broader Roles for Students," May 15, 1969 News summary - Major Events of ..., May 17, 1969 "Harvard Investigative Panel Arouses Resentment," May 21, 1969 "U. of Chicago Free of Student Unrest," May 22, 1969 (2 copies) "Hair Stylist of a Generation," Karl Shapiro, Chicago Tribune, May 25, 1969 "Yale Punishes 3 on Faculty for Accepting 12," May 28, 1969 "Day Nursery or Revolution?," David Martin (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memoranda Related to Student Protests, 1969, Edward Levi to Philip M. Hauser and Committee of Council, February 21, 1969 J. Frese to John T. Wilson et al., March 3, 1969 George W. Platzman to Charles D. O'Connell, March 3, 1969 Arnold W. Ravin to Edward Levi, March 5, 1969 J.M. Witting to J.V. Smith, March 7, 1969 The University Disciplinary Committee to Edward Rosenheim Jr., Final Report, March 21, 1969 Wayne Booth to Faculty, March 31, 1969 Charles D. O'Connell to Candidates Admitted to the University of Chicago, April 1, 1969 Charles D. O'Connell to Students and Faculty of the University of Chicago, April 8, 1969 Committee of 500+ to President Levi, April 9, 1969 James M. Redfield to Faculty and Students, April 10, 1969 Wayne C. Booth to Faculty and Students, April 14, 1969 Gilbert L. Lee, Jr. (Vice president for Business and Finance) to Students and Faculty, April 21, 1969 Charles D. O'Connell (Secretary of Faculties) to Faculty, April 22, 1969 Eddie N. William to Edward Levi et al., April 25, 1969 Sol Tax to Edward Levi, April 28, 1969 Independent Action Coalition, "Request For Prompt Action," April 29, 1969 Edward W. Rosenheim, Jr. (Spokesman of the Committee of Council) to Faculty and Students, April 30, 1969 Ned Glick to Department of Statistics Faculty, May 16, 1969 Saunders Mac Lane, May 26. 1969 Julian H. Levi to Chancellor Lawrence A. Klimpton, June 1, 1969 Roger H. Hildebrand to Students and Colleagues, October 2, 1969 Edward H. Levi, to the Faculty and Students, October 2, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence and Petitions relating to Student Protests, 1969, J. Henry Coffer, Jr., to the Chicago Maroon, February 15, 1969 Keith M. Baker et al. to Charles D. O'Connell, February 28, 1969 Petition: To the Council of the Senate from faculty members, April 3, 1969 O.J. Kleppa to William Kruskal, April 7, 1969 Toni Reed to Mr. O'Connell. April 18, 1969 Edward Levi to William Kruskal, June 24, 1969 Petition: To the Council of the University Senate, From the Department of Mathematics William Kruskal et al. endorsing the statement of Wayne Booth to the Faculty and Students of the University of Chicago (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Committee of the Council materials related to Student Protests, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous materials related to Student Protests, 1969, Complications?, March 6, 1969 Student Evaluation forms, March 8, 1969 Proposals concerning the appeals procedure, March 10, 1969 Bettelheim testimony to Congress, March 20, 1969 IAC, March 1969 Statement by Jack Metzler concerning events at the Center for Urban Studies April 21, 1969 Law Students Civil Rights Research Council, Report on Discipline at the University of Chicago, April 23, 1969 Recommendations of the FSACCSL on the Kalvan Report, May 1, 1969 Resolutions Adopted by the 55th Annual Meeting, American Association of University Professors, May 3, 1969 Address delivered by President Edward H. Levi during the annual meeting of the American Law Institute, May 23, 1969 Report of the Committee of the Council Election Held May 1969 Convocation address, President Edward H. Levi, University of Chicago, delivered at the University of Rochester, June 8, 1969 Convocation address, President Edward H. Levi, University of Chicago, June 13, 1969 The Committee of the Council, Spokesman's Report, June 16, 1969 Pamphlet: Anabaptism Reborn, September 1969 Discipline and Education: A Heurstic Statement Hyde Park Renewal: UC Racism The Fight Against Racist Urban Renewal Programs is Far From Over Rally flyer A Faculty-Student Appeals Board Notice and forms for student disciplinary action Disciplinary Procedures National Student Association Delegation Handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Harris Committee materials concerning an Afro-American Cultural Center, 1969, Council notes, "Concerning an Afro-American Cultural Center," February 1969 Memorandum, James C. Bruce to the members of the Harris Committee Outline, "Concerning an Afro-American Cultural Center" Memorandum, William Kruskal to Harris Committee, March 19, 1969 Interim report of the Committee on University Policy for Black Students Newspaper clipping, "Negro Students Criticized by Rustin, " April 28, 1969 Notes by Kruskal (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Wegener Report materials, Newspaper clipping, "Campus Boycott," September 29, 1969 Issue of Faculty/Staff Currents, Tuesday, October 7, 1969 Memorandum, Harry Roberts to Norman Nachtrieb and Committee of the Council, January 14, 1970 Memorandum, Harry Roberts to Norman Nachtrieb and Committee of the Council, January 27, 1970 Committee Selection by Statistical Sampling, Harry V. Roberts, February 1970 Memorandum, Easley Blackwood to Members of the Council of the Senate, February 9, 1970 Memorandum, Gerhard Closs et al. to Members of the University Senate, February 17, 1970 Address by Edward H. Levi, "The Manipulated Society," before the Economic Club of Chicago, February 25, 1970 Memorandum, William Kruskal to Norman Nachtrieb, March 3, 1970 Memorandum, William Kruskal to Norman Nachtrieb, April 14, 1970 (and copy) Letter, Harvey to Bill, April 16, 1970 Newpaper clipping, "Princeton's Plan," May 12, 1970 Memorandum, Knox C. Hill to Faculty and the University of Chicago, May 13, 1970 Statement of Philip B. Kurland to the Councilors of the Senate of the University of Chicago on Recommendation Four of the Wegener Committee Report Article, Styles of Handling Student Demonstrations, Merry Selk Report of the Subcommittee on Disciplinary Procedures at the University of Chicago (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Spartacus materials, Memorandum, University Disciplinary Committee to Edward H. Rosenheim, Jr., Final Report, March 21, 1969 Memorandum, University Disciplinary Committee, Dallin Oaks, April 22, 1969 Memorandum, Norval Morris to Phil Kurland, April 24, 1969 "A Statistical Review of 'Spartacus, No. 2,'" photocopied manuscript and notes, April 25, 1969 Memorandum, Edward W. Rosenheim Jr. to the faculty and students, April 30, 1969 Spartacus, 2 printed copies, May 1, 1969 Memorandum, Miron L. Straf on behalf of the authors of A Closer Look at Spartacus, Tuesday, May 27, 1969 Newspaper clipping, "Reply to Reply to Reply," Chicago Maroon, May 27, 1969 Letter, the authors of A Closer Look at Spartacus to our contributors, June 12, 1969 Untitled typescript about "Spartacus Defended," Miron L. Straf, n.d. A Closer Look at Spartacus, typescript A Closer Look at Spartacus, printed copy (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Gray Committee materials on the status of women, Memorandum, Chairman, sub-committee, to members of the Policy Committee, October 20, 1967 Statement in University Policy on Nepotism, December 1, 1967 Memorandum, Alton A. Linford to John T. Wilson, February 17, 1969 Memorandum, A.A. Albert to the Committee of the Council, February 21, 1969 Memorandum, Roald F. Campbell to John T. Wilson, February 24, 1969 Memorandum, D. Gale Johnson (Dean of the Division of Social Science) to John T. Wilson (dean of Faculties), February 28, 1968 Memorandum, Robert E. Streeter to John T. Wilson, March 13, 1969 Memorandum, Jerald C. Brauer to John T. Wilson, March 19, 1969 Memorandum, Wayne C. Booth to John T. Wilson, March 25, 1969 Memorandum, Charles D. O'Connell to the member s of the Committee of the Council, April 9, 1969 Memorandum, Edward H. Rosenheim, Jr. to faculty and students, May 6, 1969 Memorandum, Ben Rothblatt to John T. Wilson, regarding women faculty member, May 15, 1969 Committee of the Council, Agenda for a Long Meeting (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Edward H. Levi Correspondence, 1969, Leonard Sokolower to Levi, March 10, 1969 and Levi to Leonard Sokolower, March 14, 1969 (2 copies) Mrs. Richard J. Stein to Levi, March 14, 1969 and Levi to Mrs. Richard J. Stein, March 14, 1969 John Perry Miller to Kiingman Brewster, Jr., April 2, 1969 Levi to the Committee of the Council, April 4, 1969 with telegram Professor and Mrs. Ted Kazanhoff to Levi, April 5, 1969 Mr. and Mrs. Ernst Busse to Levi, April 5, 1969 Charles Handler to Levi, Apri 7, 1969 Mrs. Leonard Baron ti\o Levi, April 8, 1969 John Bremmer to Levi. April 11, 1969 William C. Lee to Levi, April 15, 1969 and Levi to William C. Lee, April 17, 1969 William Tucker to Levi, April 16, 1969 and Levi to William Tucker, April 21, 1969 Joyce K. Newman to Wayne C. Booth, April 17, 1969 Laurence N. Strenger to Levi, April 18, 1969 and Levi to Laurence N. Stringer, April 21, 1969 Saunders MacLane to Levi, April 21, 1969 and Levi to Saunders, April 24, 1969 James L. Blawie to Levi, April 25, 1969 Richard S. Albin to Levi, Aril 25, 1969 Lester Bernstein to Levi, April 23, 1969 and Levi to Lester Bernstein, April 25, 1969 Levi to Kruskal, May 16. 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Football, Urban Renewal, and Anesthesiology materials, Letter, Gary Leland to Mr. O'Connell, March 3, 1969, regarding football at the University of Chicago Memorandum, Charles D. O'Connell to the Committee of the Council, March 31, 1969, regarding the varsity status for football South Campus Committee Recommendations May 6, 1969 Plaisance Court Association Memorandum Materials on the creation of a Department of Anesthesiology, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Committee of the Council Minutes, October 8, 1968 October 17, 1968 October 22, 1968 October 29, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Faculty Committee on Government Contracts and Grants, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Restricted Access, Report on the Faculty Committee to Review the Decision with Regard to the Reappointment of Assistant Professor Marlene Dixon Disciplinary Action Notes, 1969 Status of Disciplinary Committee Actions, March 24, 1969 Inter-Department Memo, Morris Generous to Ed Shiv (Box 2, Folder 15)